<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Christian's work and time of working In a sermon preached on the death of Mr. John Sorrel the younger, of Hyde-Hall in Great Waltham in the county of Essex. By Benjamin Smith, vicar there.</title>
            <author>Smith, Benjamin, 1642 or 3-1714.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60406</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4021A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220555</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831951</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831951</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36418</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60406)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36418)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2098:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Christian's work and time of working In a sermon preached on the death of Mr. John Sorrel the younger, of Hyde-Hall in Great Waltham in the county of Essex. By Benjamin Smith, vicar there.</title>
                  <author>Smith, Benjamin, 1642 or 3-1714.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T. James, for Thomas Parkhurst at the Bible and three Crowns in Cheapside, near Mercers Chappel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With errata on p. 43 and advertisement on pp. 43-44.</note>
                  <note>Copy closely trimmed at head with slight loss of print; some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sorrel, John, d. 1675 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36418:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36418:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Chriſtian's Work</hi> AND TIME of WORKING. IN A SERMON Preached on the Death of Mr. John Sorrel the Younger, of <hi>HYDE-HALL</hi> in <hi>Great Waltham</hi> in the COUNTY of ESSEX.</p>
            <p>By <hi>BENJAMIN SMITH,</hi> Vicar there.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Eccleſ. 9. 10.</bibl> 
               <hi>Whatſoever thy hand findeth to do, do it with all thy might; for there is no work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in the Grave whither thou goeſt.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>—<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <bibl>Sophocles</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. James,</hi> for <hi>Thomas Parkhurſt</hi> at the Bible and three Crowns in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers</hi> Chappel. 1675.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:36418:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36418:2"/>
            <head>To Mrs. <hi>Sorrel</hi> the Sorrowful Relict of Mr. <hi>John Sorrel</hi> the Younger, of <hi>Hyde-Hall</hi> in <hi>Great Waltham,</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>NO Engagements could have been ſufficient to have drawn me to appear in Publick in ſo madly Cenſorious an Age as ours, did I greatly concern my ſelf at what the World will ſay: For Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is like a running the Gantlope, where a man Expoſes himſelf naked, and every man will be ſure to have a laſh at his back. The Wit and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius of the Age lyes moſt in finding fault, and ſome men will do it out of a diſlike to the perſon, and ſome to the Work, and many, that they may ſhew their judgement (as they think) and make it appear that they have wit enough to ſpy a fault. And therefore privacy is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the beſt defence againſt the petulancy of the Tongue; for he that is not known nor heard of in the World, is in no danger of being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed by the Cenſures of it. Had I therefore valued the Cenſures of Men, I had choſen rather to have diſobliged you, by denying your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, than thus to expoſe my ſelf, and run the hazard that here I do. But I hunt not after Applauſe, (and if I did, I had never ſought it by publiſhing this Sermon.) Nor do I at all concern my ſelf to think what men will ſay, or how they will judge or condemn this Work. My work muſt ſtand or fall according to my great Maſters approbation; Why then ſhould I regard what the World ſayes of it? ſince their Applauſe or Reproach can neither add nor diminiſh in the acceptance of it with him. I have therefore Obeyed your Commands, and at your Requeſt this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon is now made publick; and other Apology than this I ſhall not go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to make for my ſelf. I ſhall not tell the World what a ſenſe I have of your conſtant Civilities to me, nor plead that the Obligations that your Kindneſs hath lay'd upon me, made me unable to refuſe your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands (though I muſt own that theſe have been the prevailing Induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with me;) for when I have ſaid what I can, men will think what they pleaſe, and I am very well contented they ſhould do ſo.</p>
            <p>Nor ſhall I go about to frame an Excuſe for this Dedication, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out firſt asking your leave; for at whoſe door ſhould I lay this Sermon now it is made publick, than at yours, to whoſe Commands it entirely oweth its coming abroad. I will not doubt of its Acceptance with you, for the ſake of him who was the occaſion of it, a Perſon who though dead, yet retains that eſteem in your heart that cannot be augmented by the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Character that can be given of him, and is ſufficient to recommend to your Acceptance any thing that hath any relation to him.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:36418:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> I know too well the greatneſs of your Sorrow, and know that you are ſo fully ſenſible of your Loſs, that it would be but Cruelty to you, under the notion of Reſpect to the Dead, for me to add more weight to your load, and aggravate your loſs, in ſaying what a one he was whom you have loſt. The greatneſs of the Affection you had for him, ſhould make you the more contented in being deprived of him, ſence it is ſo much for his gain. The ſupport that God hath given you under your great affliction, and the plenty of Mercies that are ſtill left you, are great Occaſions and Engagements ſtill to be thankful, and ſhould induce you to own this providence, though ſevere, yet as the Chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Father, not as the Wound of an Enemy; he that called for this mercy again, could have called for more, and have left you much more deſolate than you are. To continue lamenting your Loſs, and to ſtand meaſuring the length, and bredth, and depth of the Affliction, and to ſurvey it in all its dimenſions, is but to look on the back-ſide of the Book, where nothing is to be learned; and which hinders you from looking in to read the Leſſon that God has written out for you by this providence. Your Work is to conſider what God deſigns in this his doing, and to labour to ſpell out the meaning of theſe black Characters. The delight of your eyes is taken away with a ſtruak, and your greateſt Comfort in this life hath failed you: Truſt then to ſuch periſhing Joyes no more, ſit looſe to the World and the blandiſhments of it, and fix with all your might your thoughts and hopes upon him, who being unchangeable, never fails, nor can fail them that put their Truſt in him. Remember him that is gone before, ſo as to prepare to Follow him; and let the memory of his Piety and Vertues be ever before your Eyes as a fair Copy to Write afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that ſince he ſhall not return to you, you may go to him, and enjoy him once again, never to loſe him more. Such as theſe, and many more, are the proper Improvements of this diſpenſation; which that you may ſo improve, as to reap the advantage of Spiritual health from this bitter Potion, is and ſhall be the ſubject of his Prayers for you to the Throne of Grace; who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               <signed>Your Humble Servant, Benjamin Smith.</signed>
               <dateline>From <hi>Much Waltham</hi> Vicaridge, <date>
                     <hi>July,</hi> 1675.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:36418:3"/>
            <head>A CHRISTIANS WORK, AND Time of Working.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>John<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9. 4.</bibl>
               <q>I muſt Work the Works of him that ſent me while it is Day; the Night cometh when no Man can Work.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AMongſt all the Uncertainties that our Affairs in this World are liable to, there is nothing that more juſtly deſerves the name of Uncertain, than the Date and Period of our Lives. Our Enjoyments indeed are fluid and brittle, and a moment is enough to deſtroy the pleaſure and grandeur of that ſtate in which we had lay'd up the Hopes of many Years happy Repoſe; but yet as fickle as theſe are, they are not more uncertain (if ſo much) as the time in which we are capable of uſing theſe En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments. A time determined indeed, if we reſpect that God in whoſe Hands the boundaries of our Times are, and who ſayes to every man as he ſaid to the Sea, <hi>Hitherto ſhalt thou come, and no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and here ſhall thy proud waves be ſtay'd:</hi> But if we reſpect our ſelves, to whom the time is allotted, we find nothing in it that is ſure and certain but this, that its end will certainly come; but when, or how ſoon, there's none that knows. Our dayes are but ſhort if we ſuppoſe them to run to their utmoſt Extent, and therefore <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, Pſalm</hi> 39. 5. compares their <hi>length to a Span;</hi> but of this little how much is liable to be cut off by Accidents and Incertainties, or by the determinations of an all-wiſe and over-ruling providence; that though we may be ſure that at their longeſt they are but as a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36418:4"/> 
               <hi>Span long,</hi> yet no man can be ſure that they ſhall be ſo much as a Span long to him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Both which brevity and uncertainty of our Lives, the Scriptures teach us, while it compares our time to things that are ſoon done, or that are very incertain in their durance. The <hi>Shepheards Tent,</hi> or the <hi>Weavers ſhuttle</hi> are fit Emblems of the ſhortneſs of our dayes, and St. <hi>James</hi> tell us, <hi>our life is even a vapour;</hi> and the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> proclaims, that <hi>all fleſh is Graſs,</hi> to ſhew how uncertain and unſtable our continuance even in this ſhort time is. And this Incertainty of our Lives muſt needs be evident to him that ſhall but conſider, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Principles we are compoſed of, or the Accidents we are lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to, or the daily Experiences we have of it.</p>
            <p>The Principles we are compoſed of are different in their Nature, and repugnant one to another, hot and cold, moiſt and dry, by the Wiſdom and Power of God are tempered together in the duſt that makes up our Frame; theſe diſcordant Humors are alwaies at va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance amongſt themſelves, and there is an Inteſtime War conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually maintain'd, that threatens the ruin of the whole Frame. How eaſily may one Humor get the upper hand of all the reſt? and yet our ſafety conſiſts in the equal temperature of them; and if one prevail, the Body is deſtroyed by the Tyranny and Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominance of that one Humor: ſo that our Lives depend upon the ſucceſs of a ſcuffle, and are uncertain as the chance of War.</p>
            <p>But beſides theſe, how numerous and various are External ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, who knows what a Night may produce? or what may be in the Womb of a Morning? Who can ſay that his path is ſecure, or that no Creature has received a Commiſſion to day to take away his Life, the very Inanimate Creatures are ſufficiently armed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Lives if God does but give the Word, and the wayes to effect it are too many, and too different for our Wiſdom or Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to fore-ſee or prevent.</p>
            <p>And to all this, the undeniable proof of Experience may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, our dayes are uncertain beyond diſpute, for almoſt every day we have Inſtances that confirm it. Death does not wait upon the courſe of Nature, nor obſerve the order of Birth, but ſhoots his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows hood-winkt among the Herd. He ſnatches the tender Infant from its Mothers breaſt, and cuts off the Young-man in the midſt of his ſtrength and dayes, as well as gathers the Hoary head <hi>(like a Shock of Corn in his ſeaſon)</hi> into the Grave. The Young and Old, the Weak and Strong are huddled together in the Duſt, and there is no
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36418:4"/> Age or State that can ſecure and make us free from Deaths arreſt. Here he fells the full grown Oak, and there he cuts up the tender Speers, and every dayes Experience makes the Proverb good, <hi>viz.</hi> As ſoon goes the green Tree to the Fire as the dry.</p>
            <p>What ſhould man do then, whom Scripture, and Reaſon, and Experience daily convince of the incertainty of his life? Or to what end is he made ſo palpably ſure that he is at no certain ſtay here? but that he might lift up his thoughts to what is more firm, and improve the preſent Seaſons (which only weare ſure of) to the obtaining an Eternal and Unchangeable ſtate: For ſince this Life, as incertain as it is, is in order to a Future ſtate, which once en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred upon, admits of no alteration; that our Lives are uncertain, does earneſtly call upon us to haſten our Work, and improve our time, that we may be ready for our Change whenſoever it comes. That we muſt dye, and come to Judgment, makes it neceſſary for us to prepare for death; but ſince we know not but that we may dye to morrow, it's neceſſary that we provide for its coming to day.</p>
            <p>This then is the Uſe we ſhould make of all the <hi>Memento</hi>'s we have of Mortality, or of the incertainty or frailty of our Lives; and we ſhould never ſee or hear of any ſnatcht away from us, but it ſhould haſten us in our Work, and make us more diligent to prepare for our turn; for who knows whoſe is next?</p>
            <p>And to this end I have been deſired to apply this ſad and ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing providence that has lately befallen one of the Chiefeſt Families in our Pariſh, that ſeeing a Young-man cut off near the midſt of his dayes, thoſe that are left, both Young and Old may lay it to heart, and be awakened, to conſider by this Inſtance how uncertain our time is, that they may be ſtirred up to mind their Work in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time, leſt their End prevent their Preparations for it.</p>
            <p>And to this end I have been directed to this Portion of Scripture, as giving a ſufficient Ground to build ſuch an Exhortation upon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I muſt Work the Works of him that ſent me while it is day, the night cometh when no man can Work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Words that are capable of a Two-fold Application, as they are the Reaſon of our Saviours practice, and as they are Rule of ours: As they are the reaſon of our Saviours acting, ſo they were ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by our Saviour of himſelf, and have a peculiar Relation to himſelf; but the Reaſon they are founded upon, makes them a Rule
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36418:5"/> to us, and from that they are an argument reaching ever to us to be diligent and ſedulous in our buſineſs.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour was ſent into the World to work the great work of our Redemption, and as he came into the world, <hi>and the Word was made Fleſh,</hi> that he might dye; ſo was he while he was upon Earth, to prove his Miſſion from the Father, and by the works he wrought, convince the World that he was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> he that was to come.</p>
            <p>And therefore having here found a Subject fit to manifeſt his power upon, and by a Miracle to manifeſt his Miſſion, he does not ſtay to diſpute or debate the impertinent and erroneous Quaere of his Diſciples, <hi>Who ſinn'd, this man or his Parents, that he was born blind?</hi> but denying both parts of the Queſtion, haſtens to the Cure, and that upon this Reaſon, <hi>I muſt work the works, &amp;c.</hi> that is, I muſt take all opportunities to do the Works about which I am ſent into the world, and make uſe of my preſent time, for my death is coming, by which theſe works muſt have an end. Where his reaſon of working while it is day, being founded upon the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral reaſon of approaching death, the words will be found to be of equal extent with the Reaſon they are built upon, and are a ſtrong Argument for the like diligence to every one that is under the like circumſtances of Mortality: If therefore there be the ſame reaſon for us to be diligent in minding and haſtning our work that we have to do, that there was for him to mind and haſten his, theſe words will be found to concern us, and be to us as well as to our Saviour an undeniable reaſon of diligence in our work while we have life and time. And this a ſhort Enquiry into the ſenſe and importance of the words will prove:</p>
            <p>And in them we may conſider theſe three things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That our Saviour had works to do, <hi>I muſt work the works of him that ſent me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That he took the preſent time, and lay'd hold upon every op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity that offered it ſelf to do theſe Works in: <hi>I muſt work the works of him that ſent me while it is day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Reaſon why he did thus, and ſo carefully lay'd hold on every ſeaſon to do his Works in, was, leaſt the night ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent him; <hi>the night cometh when no man can work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt Conſideration I ſhall wholly wave, for thought it be worth our Enquiry what the Works were he had to do, and by whom he was ſent; and how he that was in his own Nature God
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36418:5"/> bleſſed for evermore, could be ſent by any, ſince being God he could have no Super<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or to ſend him; and ſo upon the ſame Reaſon how the works he did (he being God) could be the works, or by the appointment of any other but himſelf, (which may all be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by conſidering the diſtinction of his Nature and his Office:) yet ſince the conſidering theſe is not pertinent to my preſent purpoſe, the force of the words as to the buſineſs in hand lying in his dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in working, and in the reaſon he gives of it, it may ſuffice to have obſerved that he had works to do, without entring into any diſcourſe concerning the nature of them, or the accounts upon which he was obliged to perform them.</p>
            <p>I ſhall paſs therefore from this to what is more pertinent to the preſent purpoſe, and conſider.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he took the preſent time to do his works in, and this is implyed in that expreſſion, <hi>I muſt work, while it is day.</hi> (To wave here the curious Criticiſms and Conjectures of ſome upon the day here mentioned) by day here I underſtand the time of this life here upon earth, and ſo our Saviour ſaying, <hi>I muſt work while it is day,</hi> the meaning is, I muſt be doing the <hi>works of him that ſent me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> now while I am upon earth, now while I am in the fleſh: So <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phylact,</hi> the day is this preſent life. And <hi>Piſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ator</hi> to the ſame ſenſe he compares the courſe of his life upon earth to a <hi>day;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is the time of Life called a day, with an eſpecial reſpect and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to working. The day is a time, and the only time for work, the night is appointed for reſt, and ſo is our life the only time of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what is to be done in order to our Eternal ſtate; in death we reſt from our Labours. Our Saviour therefore would let no op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity paſs of doing good while it was day, that is, while the time of his life upon Earth laſted; and that for the Reaſon which he gives in the next words, <hi>The night cometh when no man can work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that is the thing which comes next to be conſidered, to give an account why he was ſo diligent in working, and the Text tells us,</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Reaſon why he did thus, and ſo carefully lay'd hold on the preſent ſeaſon, was, leſt the night ſhould prevent him; <hi>the night comes when no man can work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In what ſenſe the night is here to be taken, is eaſie to underſtand, by what has been ſaid of the day, to which this anſwers. For if that means the time of this life, then by Night muſt here be meant the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36418:6"/> time of death; for this Reaſon then our Saviour ſays he muſt work while he lived, becauſe death was coming, in which we have a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Reaſon couched:</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the nearneſs of it, <hi>the night cometh;</hi> it is not ſaid, it will come, but it does come, in that implying that it was now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching, and already upon his Journey towards him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From the effect of it when come, <hi>No man can work.</hi> As if he had ſaid, I muſt now do what I have to do while I have time and life, my time is not long, my death cometh, and is at hand; and when that's once come, theſe Works of mine muſt ceaſe; for in death no man can work: parallel to which Reſolution and Reaſon is the advice and argument of the Wiſe man, <hi>Eccleſ. 9. 10. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever thine hand findeth to do, do it with all thy might, for there is no work, nor device, nor knowledg, nor wiſdom in the Grave, whither thou goeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And having thus briefly cleared the ſence and importance of the Words, and conſidered the reaſon and foundation they ſtand upon, there is no man but at the very firſt ſight muſt needs conclude, that the Caſe is ours. We are under the ſame Circumſtances that he was, and the ſame Reaſon that prevailed with him to diligence in his Work is much more urgent upon us.</p>
            <p>Had he Works to do? ſo have we: Was death approaching to him, and was he mortal as he was a man? certainly and undeniably ſo are we. If then it was a good Reaſon for him to make haſt to do his Work, becauſe he muſt dye, undoubtedly the Reaſon is as ſtrong towards us, for we muſt dye too; and after death there is no more working for us in our Works, than there was for him in his.</p>
            <p>It cannot be denied then, but the words belong to us, and are a neceſſary Rule of our practice, and a ſtrong Reaſon to ſpur us on to diligence in the work we have to do in this preſent Life. I ſhall therefore take them (ſince they cannot be denyed me) and apply the meaning of them to our practice in this Doctrinal Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>That we ought to be Diligent in doing our Work that we have to do, while we have time and life; becauſe Death cometh, where no Work can be done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Leſſon needful to be learn't, becauſe it is of great importance to us in order to our Eternal welfare, and ſo much the rather need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful becauſe the practice of too many tells us, that they underſtand
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36418:6"/> not this Leſſon, nor are convinc'd of the neceſſity of it. Some do not underſtand their Work, and ſo, though they take much pains, and are very buſie, their Work turns to no account, becauſe though they have done much, they have done nothing at all of what God ſent them to do. Some underſtand not their time, and though they may know their Work, yet alwayes think it too ſoon to ſet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> about it yet, and ſo drive off and delay till their day be done before, they begin their work. Both theſe ought to conſider and weigh this truth, that we ought to be diligent in doing our work, while we have time; the one to conſider that we ought to be employed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout our work, and be doing what we were ſent to do; and the other to learn that we ought to lay hold upon time while we have it, and work while it is day; and the Reaſon is the ſame to both, becauſe of approaching death, <hi>the night cometh when no man can work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That therefore I may offer ſomewhat towards the direction of the one, and the awakning of the other, I ſhall conſider, and ſpeak to this Propoſition, by way of Enquiry into theſe three Things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What is the Work we have to do?</p>
            <p n="2">2. What is the time this Work ought to be done in?</p>
            <p n="3">3. What is the Reaſon why thoſe Works ought to be done at that time, and not to be put off to any other?</p>
            <p>1. What is the Work that we have to do?</p>
            <p>That we have Works to do, may well be taken for granted, for it cannot be well ſuppoſed, that man ſhould have a time given him, and nothing to do with that time, nor no employment for it aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him. It cannot be well ſuppoſed that man ſhould be entruſted with many Tallents, and be endued with many excellent and uſeful Faculties above other Creatures, and yet be deſigned to be more idle and uſeleſs than they. And yet as unreaſonable as this is to be ſuppoſed, there are thoſe in the World who had need be convinc'd of this truth; there are thoſe who had need be told that God has appointed employments to ſpend our time in, and that they need not go hunt for diverſions, nor invent wayes to drive on the weariſom hours that fly too faſt away of themſelves. There are thoſe that had need be told that God has given us a Faculty of Reaſon and Judgment for other ends than to be able to paſs a Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure upon a Garb or Dreſs, or to be able to give a Judgment upon anothers Gate, Meen, or Behaviour. In ſhort, how many had need to be told that God gave us our time for ſomewhat elſe than for Play and Sport, for other ends than to pamper the fleſh, and be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36418:7"/> wanton, and that when he ſent us into this World to live, he never intended we ſhould paſs our dayes like Drones, and be lazy.</p>
            <p>I muſt therefore in the firſt place conſider the works that we have to do, and all the Enquiry here will be, what Works thoſe are in which this our time ought to be imployed. And this enquiry would juſtly deſerve a longer time to be ſpent in it then I have now to ſpare; for ſurely the moſt of men know not their Works, or are hardly perſwaded what their buſineſs is, or elſe they would never neglect it as they do, nor weary themſelves ſo much in doing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or in doing miſchief, for want of a better employment.</p>
            <p>Now the Text may ſerve to direct us what our Work is; for though the Works that our Saviour was ſent to do, and the Works that we have to do, are vaſtly different as to their own nature, yet in this they agree that both his Works and ours are the Works of him that ſent us. God is our Maſter, and we are ſent into the World upon his Errand, and he that gave us our Being, hath alſo appointed the deſign and end of it. We are ſent into the World upon buſineſs, not as ſome Youths are ſent to Travel, to gaze upon the World, and ſee Faſhions, and gather up the Vanities of the Times, but as Embaſſadors to negotiate and tranſact ſome buſineſs for our Maſters Honor, or like Factors to Trade with, and improve our Talents for our Maſters advantage.</p>
            <p>And having ſaid that our work that we have to do here, is the work of him that ſent us; I have ſaid enough to prove the generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the World to be idle or worſe imploy'd. For how eaſily is it ſeen, that the works that moſt men ſpend their time in, are ſuch as they that do them, dare not aſcribe to God as the Author or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of them. God never ſent us hither to make proviſion for the Fleſh, to fulfil the luſts thereof; he never ſet us to ſcrape for Wealth, and to ſeek for all advantages to be Rich or Great; he never made it our buſineſs nor ſet us this for our work, to follow our inordinate affections through all thoſe dangerous and uncouth ways in which they hurry us on; he never ſent us hither to be vicious or debaucht, to be intemperate or unclean, to be ambitious or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengful; nor to ſet the world on Fire with the Heat and exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy of our paſſions: and yet theſe are the works in which the moſt of the World employ themſelves.</p>
            <p>The works of him that ſent us bear his Stamp and Image upon them, and are like to him that ſent us to do them, they are ſuch as become him to appoint who is the Author of them, and ſuch as
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36418:7"/> will make us like unto Him, if we carefully practice and do them.</p>
            <p>He has ſent us hither to learn to know him, and to be conform'd to his Image in Righteouſneſs and True Holineſs; he has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us to learn his will and to do it, to be ſerviceable to him in our generation and to be uſeful to one another in our ſeveral ſpheres and places; he has call'd us to mortifying the luſts of the Fleſh, to growth in grace, and all Chriſtian vertues; he has call'd us to meekneſs and gentleneſs, and to the mutual acts of love and kindneſs one to another; to ſeek every one the welfare of another before our own, he has enjoyn'd us compaſſion and charity; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires that we be tender-hearted, and that we forbear and mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly forgive one another: He has command us to be peaceable and quiet, and rather to recede from our own right, then to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broyle the world or diſquiet our neighbours by our petty or infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Concerns. In ſhort, he has made this our buſineſs, for which we come here, to act in order to his Glory and our own Salvation, which two ends he has ſo twined together, that they become inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably one, and he that faithfully labours for the one, cannot fail of obtaining the other.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the ends of our being, which he that made us has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed; and this is a rough draught and a ſhort ſummary of the Works we have to do in this life. Such as theſe are the Works that God has ſent us to do, and whatſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ves actions are contrary to theſe, are none of our Work, nay contrary to it; and when we come to our account, will be found to be a deceiving our Maſter, an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bezling our time, and a contradicting the ends of our Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But that we may have a more perfect Scheme, and a fairer draught of our work before our eyes, let us conſider man as ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in a two ſold Relation, in the one towards God, in the other towards man. The conſideration of which two Relations will preſent us with thoſe general Hoods, under which the whole duty of man is comprized. It is not to be expected that I ſhould give a diſtinct account of every particular work and employment that is appointed man to do in this world, that cannot be the work of an hour, or be comprized within the limits of one ſingle Sermon, my deſign is only to give you thoſe Heads unto which our particular du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties may be referred; and may ſerve as a Memorial to us, by the help of which we may the better call to mind our particular Duties, and be put in mind of the practice of them.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:36418:8"/>
            <p>1. The firſt Relation we ſtand in is towards God, and that may be conſidered two wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As we are his Creatures.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As we are ſinners againſt him.</p>
            <p>From both theſe different Conſiderations, different works ariſe, which are our duty to do, and which it is neceſſary that they ſhould be done before the Night comes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As we are his Creatures. And ſo there lyes an Obligation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us to do whatſoever God has enjoyned us, it being but Reaſon that he that made us ſhould have the full diſpoſal of us; we look to have the uſe of what our hands have made, and we being as the Apoſtle ſayes, <hi>Epheſ. 2. 10. The workmanſhip of God,</hi> it were unjuſt and unreaſonable to deny that God has the full power to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point and aſſign us what employment he ſees fit. And therefore we are not to conſult our own Fancies, nor be guided by our own incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations what we ſhall do, or how we ſhall live now we are come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, but we muſt receive our Errand from his mouth, and attend to him for directions how to ſpend our time. VVe muſt look to the manifeſtations of his mind, and the Revelations of his will, we muſt liſten to what God has commanded; for what God has bidden us to do, that is our work, and ſo we muſt employ our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Now this being conſidered, that we are juſtly at Gods diſpoſal by the Law of our Creation, and none can claim any intereſt in us, nor any ſhare in our time or ſervice, contrary to what God has appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it will further follow, that being wholly his, and at his diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, our whole time and abilities ought to be employed in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and for his Glory; for as the Scriptures refer our Being to God, and every where teach us that he is the Creator of us, and all things, ſo they farther inſtruct us, that the deſign of all things was his own glory, which for us to deny at any time, or in any inſtance to be ſerviceable to, is to fruſtate the ends of our Creator, and to contradict the deſign of our being. <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>Prov. 16. 4. That the Lord hath made all things for himſelf;</hi> and the Apoſtle gives us this ſtrict charge, 1 <hi>Cor. 10. 31. Whatſoever ye do, do all to the Glory of God,</hi> ſo that as all that we have, our being, and the enjoyments we poſſeſs in it, are the bounty of God; ſo muſt all be referr'd to him again, in an induſtrious imployment of all for his ſervice and glory. So that to be idle and uſeleſs in the World, and to do no good, will be ſound to be againſt the deſign of our Creation, as really,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36418:8"/> though not it may be ſo much, as is our imploying our ſelves in evil &amp; doing miſchief; for when our Reaſon will not permit us to imagine that God by his power ſhould make us, and by his daily providence preſerve us and feed us with his bounty, and this for no other ends as Ladies keep Doggs to lie and ſleep in their Laps.</p>
            <p>By the Law then of our Creation we owe our ſelves entirely to God, and as we are his Creatures, we ought to be alwayes em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in his Service. And ſo univerſal Obedience is our duty and task, which though through our weakneſs, we are not able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, yet 'tis our duty to will and endeavour it; for a willing fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieur in our duty, and a deſigned omiſſion of any point and part of our due Obedience, is not a frailty and infirmity of Nature, but contumacy, and willful Rebellion.</p>
            <p>And from what has thus far been ſaid concerning our Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that we ought alwayes to be engaged in this ſervice of God, will appear the folly and unreaſonableneſs of thoſe that talk of ſerving God hereafter, that neglect their duty now, and talk of doing it another time; for theſe do not regard, nor weigh that all our time is to be employed for God, and that he has ſet us our work, and given an employment for every day of our lives. And therefore to ſay I will ſerve ſin now, and obey the luſts of the fleſh to day, or (to put in gentler terms) to ſay I will loyter and be idle now, or take my eaſe, and be lazy to day, and will ſerve God to morrow, or ſet about my work hereafter, is in effect to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, God has ſet me thus much work to do, but I do not intend to do it all, I will be ſure to omit ſome of it now, and it may be I will do ſome of it hereafter.</p>
            <p>For if God commands me to ſerve him all the dayes of my life, (as by the very Law of Creation he does) then am I bound to ſerve him to day as well as to morrow; and if I neglect his ſervice to day, I cannot any wayes make him amends by doing my duty to morrow, for what I may do to morrow, can be no more than to morrow's ſervice, that is no more than the work of one day, and ſo cannot poſſibly in ſtrictneſs and juſtice be any Reparation for my former neglect. So that every day that we neglect, or defer our duty, or otherwiſe employ our ſelves, we rob God of the ſervice we owe him, and contradict the end for which we were made, in that we do not the works of him that ſent us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We may be conſidered as ſinners againſt God, and this we are as ſoon as we are born, and as ſoon as we begin to be, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36418:9"/> to be evil. By one man ſin entred into the world, and from him it paſſed upon all men, upon thoſe that had not ſinned after the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of his trangreſſion, even before we are actual ſinners as he was, there is a depravation of our Natures, an enmity in us againſt God, and a perverſe diſpoſal, and inclination as ſoon as we are able to act, to act amiſs. <hi>David</hi> gives us an account, what in our firſt principles and beginnings we are, while he ſayes, <hi>Pſalm 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 5. Behold I was ſhapen in iniquity, and in ſin did my Mother con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive me;</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, what the iſſue and effect of that Original depravation is, in ſtiling us, <hi>Epheſ. 2. 3. by nature the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath.</hi> By nature we are ſinners, and we are daily ſuch more or leſs by our practice; for what can be the iſſue and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of a depraved nature, but a polluted and impure Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Job 14. 4. For who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean one? n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t one.</hi> And by this Original and Actual Sin we are by nature from our very beginnings, and every day by our practice, more and more the children of Wrath, and liable to the juſt Vengeance of God our Creator.</p>
            <p>This ſtate and conſideration ſuper-induces a new Work that we have to do, which though it was none of thoſe which man was ſent to do as he was made at firſt, (for the Wiſe man bears witneſs, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7. 29. that <hi>God made man pure,)</hi> yet man having ſinn'd, this is a work that God in mercy calls him to, and is as neceſſary in order to his Eternal welfare as any he can be employed in.</p>
            <p>And ſo the works that we have to do upon this conſideration are to make our peace with God, and to reform and amend our lives and wayes, our work is now to believe in Jeſus Chriſt, and truly and ſeriouſly to repent us of our ſins By the Law of Creation God calls us to univerſal Obedience, and the firſt Covenant was, <hi>Do this and live;</hi> but by the Covenant of Grace, we are called to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and repent; and this is the only remedy againſt the rigor and ſeverities of that Law.</p>
            <p>This is a Work that is neceſſary to be done, and neceſſary to be done <hi>while it is day;</hi> for if our peace be not made with God, we are irrecoverably loſt, and muſt needs be miſerable for ever. Who ſhall ſecure us from the wrath of an incenſed God, or where, or with what hopes can we appear, or ſtand in the judgment, if we have no advocate to plead our cauſe with the Father, and have no intereſt in that ſatisfaction which Chriſt made to Divine Juſtice. No Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean thing can enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, for an impure
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36418:9"/> Soul is a contradiction to the enjoyments, or ſociety, or works of that ſtate and place. If our hearts are not purified by the blood of Chriſt, and a ſound and ſincere Repentance, if our Luſts be not mortified, and our evil wayes firſt reformed, as it is impoſſible that ſo unclean a thing as ſuch a man can be admitted into a ſtate of the greateſt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rity and bliſs; ſo would it be impoſſible (could he be admitted there) that ſuch a one could take any delight in it. For ſince the pleaſure of every enjoyment conſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s in the ſuitablneſs that it hath to the mind and nature of him that enjoyes it, how can Spiritual things be Joyes to a Carnal mind, or Heaven be a place of delight to an Earthly minded man? Wrap the Swine in fine linnen, and perfume him with ſweet Odours, and you do him no kindneſs in all this, he had rather be wallowing in the mire; and ſo would the joyes of Heaven be to a ſenſual, carnal, impure minded man, there being no ſuitableneſs between his Affections and thoſe Joyes. Sin muſt then firſt become a Burden to us, and be matter of ſorrow and real grief; our Affections muſt firſt be refin'd from ſenſuality and impure delights, before they can be made capable of reliſhing ſuch ſublime Joyes, and taſting the ſweetneſs of a Society and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment ſo all pure as that is. In ſhort, we muſt be born again, and that of the Spirit, before we can either enter into, or delight in the glories and happineſs of that place.</p>
            <p>And as Repentance and Reformation are works thus neceſſary to be done, ſo to be done, <hi>while it is day;</hi> it being the neceſſary work of every day, 'tis neceſſary that we repent of every diſobedience, for every ſin unrepented of is damning; and therefore ſince we dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſin, a daily Repentance and Amendment is needful. And ſurely, he may well be ſaid to be more then mad, that defers theſe Works to another time, and will dare to delay his Repenting till too mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; for if we dye before our peace with God is made, and are ſnatcht away before we Repent, we are loſt, we periſh for ever; and yet to him that defers to do theſe Works while he may, and will needs be putting them off till another time, 'tis no impoſſible thing but that he may die before theſe Works be done. 'Tis ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary that the work be done, 'tis abſolutely as uncertain whether he that neglects to day, ſhall have to morrow to do it in; common prudence then ſhould teach us in a matter of ſo great concern to cloſe with the ſurer ſide, and lay hold upon the time that we are ſure of; not venturing our Souls upon what may fail, nor deferring the means of happineſs till too morrow, which whether it will ever come or no, we know not.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:36418:10"/>
            <p>That Repentance is a means of blotting out ſins through Faith in Chriſt, is a great Encouragement to our ſpeedy ſetting about it; but they that think it ſo eaſie to Repent, that they put it off to many years hence, or to Old Age, or a Sick-bed, may perchance be found to have been miſtaken, both in the nature of the thing, and the time of it; for ſurely 'tis not ſo ſhort a work to Repent, as ſome would make it, nor is the time that is future ſo certain to us, as that we ſhould venture ſo weighty a Concern upon it. 'Tis not every crying God mercy, or ſaying that we are ſorry; 'tis not a ſigh and a dejected look that God will accept for a true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; it requires a more inward work upon the heart, and more ſevere mortifications than theſe are; and whether this be a work ſo fit for a Sick-bed, they would do well firſt to conſider, that think of turning this work over to ſuch a time.</p>
            <p>The ſum of all is this, Repentance is a work incumbent on us as ſinners, which if it be not done before we die, we are miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for ever; and therefore we ought to do this work while it is day; 'tis dangerous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o put it off till another time, leſt that time ſhould never come; for if we refuſe the time that is preſent, we have no aſſurance of what is future. To which I ſhall add no more, but that excellent Saying of St. <hi>Auſtin, Deus qui poenitenti tibi promiſit veniam, poenitentia tua non promiſit craſtinum.</hi> That is to ſay, <hi>God indeed hath promiſed pardon to him that repents, but never promiſed us too morrow to repent in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus much may ſuffice to have ſpoken concerning thoſe works that ariſe from that relation which we ſtand in towards God, whether as his creatures or as ſinners againſt him.</p>
            <p>2. There is another relation we ſtand in as men, and that as we ſtand related one towards another. From the former relation aroſe thoſe duties which were due from man towards God; from this ariſe thoſe duties which are between man and man, and due from one man to another.</p>
            <p>And here, though the Subject be changed, yet the duties, as to the Author of them, remain the ſame; and thoſe works that we have to do upon this account, are alſo the works of him that ſent us. For whatſoever the duties are that are to be performed from man to man, they are therefore to be performed, becauſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God, and enjoyn'd us as ur duty by him, in whoſe power and right it is to determine our work, for whomſoever it is to be done. And therefore is our duty to man equally part of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36418:10"/> our works that we have to do here, becauſe enjoyned us by the ſame authority that has the ſoveraign diſpoſal of us. He that has ſaid, <hi>Luke 10. 27. Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoul, and with all thy ſtrength, and with all thy mind;</hi> the ſame hath ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this relation engages us in different works, according as our ſtation in which we ſtand in among men, may be different; for we may be conſidered,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Either in general as we are men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Or as we are men placed by God in ſome certain relation and ſphere to act in. From both of which there are ſeveral duties in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent on us, which we ought to do; and for the neglect of which we ſhall be accountable before him who has made them our work; and appointed us thoſe things to do, in thoſe ſtations wherein he has ſet us.</p>
            <p>1. We may be conſidered in general as we are men, and of the ſame nature with the reſt of mankind, and as we are ſuch, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto us thoſe general duties of love and beneficence, and of doing good mutually, as it lies in our power one to another. Under this head may be reduced all the duties of the Second Table, and as we are to be conſidered in this notion, that command of the Apoſtle belongs unto us, <hi>Gal. 6. 10. As therefore we have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, let us do good to all men.</hi> We ought to concern our ſelves for their ſouls, by good advice, and by ſeaſonable reproo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions, endeavoring to deliver them from the paths of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer, and taking the more care of our own wayes; leſt our go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſtray ſhould encourage and embolden others to do the like: and our evil example, either deſtroy, or endanger our Neighbours ſoul. We are to endeavor and deſire their temporal welfare too, to ſafeguard their lives, if it lie in our power; to vindicate their good names, and to communicate of our ſubſtance to their ſupport and relief, if they are in want. For we are not made for our ſelves, nor ſent into the world to live alone in the midſt of the earth; but as God has link'd us in ſociety with others, ſo has he commanded us to be uſeful one to another; and this is to be ſerviceable to God in our generation, by being ſerviceable to the glory of God in our ſeveral ſpheres and places; and by being the channels to convey the goodneſs and mercy of God towards others.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:36418:11"/>
            <p>And therefore it was but a ſurly Anſwer of <hi>Cain's</hi> to God, <hi>Am I my brothers keeper?</hi> For certainly God has made us ſo far keepers one of another, that if any detriment comes to our neighbour, which it lay in our power to prevent; we may juſtly be accounted before God as acceſſories at leaſt to the evil.</p>
            <p>And as churliſh was that of <hi>Nabal</hi> to <hi>David</hi>'s Meſſengers, <hi>Shall I take my bread and my water, and my fleſh, and give them to men that I know not whence they be?</hi> For thoſe that are really in need and ſtraits, have a right to relief from us; and God has not onely made it a duty, but over and above declares it a ſervice that is pleaſing to him; if we will believe the Apoſtle, who gives us this account of it, <hi>Heb. 13. 16. To do good and to communicate forget not, for with ſuch ſacrifices God is well pleaſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From whence theſe two Corolaries plainly offer themſelves to obſervation;</p>
            <p n="1">1. In vain then do men boaſt of a negative righteouſſneſs, and pleaſe or ſatisfie themſelves in that they can ſay they do no hurt, they are no knaves no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thieves, they neither cheat nor oppreſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; when for all this it may be they live like drones upon the earth, and are uſeleſs perſons, and make no body the better for them. There is a ſevere prohibition againſt doing wrong, and they do well that obey that; but there is alſo a ſtrict charge that we do good, and they ſin that obey not that. And indeed they that are onely negatively good, are not really ſo good as they imagine themſelves to be; for in vain do they boaſt that they do no wrong, ſince it is a wrong to with-hold good from whom it is due. We ought not to wrong and oppreſs our poor neighbour, this muſt be carefully obſerved, but yet there is more to be done for our poor neighbour than this; for being poor, he is the object of our chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and we muſt relieve him. We ought not to wrong the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs nor pervert the cauſe of the widdow; but this prohibition means not onely what it ſays but more, and we are commanded to plead the cauſe of the widdow, and to defend the fatherleſs. In ſhort, let that Sentence of our Saviour be weighed, and the grounds it goes upon, which is recorded <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. 41, 42, 43. and this will be enough to ſpoil the negative Chriſtians confidence. For that ſad and diſmal ſentence that is there pronounced, is not upon the account of doing evil, but for not doing good; they are not charg'd with oppreſſion or extortion, nor condemned for caſting the Members of Chriſt into priſon; but becauſe they did not
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36418:11"/> cloath and feed the hungry and naked, and did not viſit the Sick and Impriſoned.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In vain do men boaſt of a Religion towards God, that obſerve no Conſcience towards man: In vain do we keep up Religious Duties, and pretend to be ſtrict Obſervers of the Injunctions of our Maker in thoſe Duties that relate more immediatly to his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, while we reject thoſe commands that are enforc'd upon us by the ſame Authority, although relating to a different Subject. That Religion is in vain that makes it my duty to pray often and earneſtly to God, and yet never tyes my Hands from injuſtice and fraud, but allows me to oppreſs or deceive my Neighbour. That Religion is in vain that engages my tongue to ſpeak well of God, and employs it frequently in diſcourſe of Religion, and pious matters; but at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times leaves it at liberty to back-bite and ſlander, to cenſure unchantably, or bitterly to reproach anothers actions, and ſecretly to ſtrike through and wound my Neighbours Repute and Good Name. And if this ſeem to any to be too hardly ſpoken, as that of Saint <hi>James</hi> is my authority, ſo let it be my anſwer, <hi>James 1. 26. If any man among you ſeem to be religious, and bridleth not his tongue, but deceiveth his own heart, this mans religion is vain.</hi> And certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, 'tis to no purpoſe to think to bribe or blind Heaven by the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and ſedulous performance of ſome Duties that we may be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther allowed or conniv'd at in the groſs neglect of others; righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs towards man is our duty, and is part of our work to do; if we neglect this, we neglect our duty, and do not work the works of him tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> us, becauſe as he ſent us to live in Holineſs towards him; ſo he has alſo made it our duty to live in righteouſneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our Neighbour.</p>
            <p>And thus as we may be conſidered as men in general, there are works that are incumbent on us in that relation; and as we are men, we have a ſervice to do for God to Man; and 'tis an equal Violation of the Law of God, to rob God, or to wrong Man, ſince God has equally forbidden both. Much Sacrifice will not expiate that ſin, nor many prayers drown the voice of its cry; nothing but repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and a reformation of our Injuſtice and Immorality, nothing but a ceaſing to do evil, and a learning to do the contrary good, will procure our acceptance with God; and therefore we have him in the Prophet expoſtulating with his people, who were highly injurious towards man, and yet pretended to be extreamly Religious to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God. They even cloy'd him with the fat of their fed Beaſts,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36418:12"/> and even darkned Heaven with the clouds of Incenſe; they obſerved exactly their New Moons and Feaſts, their Sabbaths, and Solemn Aſſemblies; but withall practiced Injuſtice and Rapine, and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and their hands were full of Blood; they had no pitty to the Poor, nor mercy to the Widdow, nor regard to the Fatherleſs Children; God therefore declares his diſlike of their Religious ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, becauſe of their defect in theſe moral duties, and calls them firſt to the practice of them, and then promiſes to hear and accept them in the others.</p>
            <p>Let us rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and weigh the firſt chapter of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> from the <hi>10th. verſe</hi> to the <hi>21th.</hi> and there we ſhall f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd our duty in this caſe, and find this made good, that a Religion towards God without a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience towards man, is defective, and in vain.</p>
            <p>Our Work then that we are ſent to do relates to Man as well as God, and that as we are conſidered in general as men.</p>
            <p>2. But we may farther be conſidered as we are men placed by God in ſome particular Relation and Sphear to act in, whether as Magiſtrate or Miniſter, as Maſter or Servant, as Husband or Wife, as Parent or Child; theſe and the like ſeveral Relations and Places call for ſeveral Works from us, which are our duties as ſo related, and as ſet in thoſe places. Of theſe a care muſt be had, for in theſe al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o we ſerve him that ſent us; and he that is a faithful Labourer, a good Chriſtian will not, nay dare not neglect theſe.</p>
            <p>The conſideration of all which, ſhews that a Chriſtians life was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver deſigned for Jollity or Idleneſs: Having given you a ſight of thus much Work to be done, without ſaying any more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently proved, that we have no time to ſpare in wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> we may lawfully ſit ſtill, and do nothing; our Work and our Time are equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly matched, for as long as we live we muſt be doing. Much leſs can we find any time to do evil in, or to ſerve the fleſh, or to be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental to the carrying on of the deſigns of the Kingdom of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for God made us for himſelf, and gave us our time to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in his Service, and 'tis no leſs than robbing of God, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unfaithful in our truſt, to give any part of it to the ſervice of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</p>
            <p>Thus much may ſuffice to have ſpoken of the Work we have to do.</p>
            <p>2. The next thing to be conſidered, is the time when this Work ought to be done, a thing almoſt as material to be enquired after as the Work it ſelf; for as ſome miſtake, or are ignorant of their
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36418:12"/> Work, ſo it may be more miſtake the true notion of their time, and therefore defer it becauſe they think the time not yet come to begin or ſet about it. This time the Text ſays, is <hi>while it is day,</hi> and the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of that has been ſhown to be while the time of Life laſts, for the Text plainly excludes Eternity from being a ſeaſon for work; for it tells us if this Life be at an end, ſo is our work too, <hi>the Night cometh wherein no man can Work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſince the time of this Life may be divided into three parts, paſt, preſent, and to come, all the matter of our Enquiry will be, Which of theſe three is our working time in which we ought to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our ſelves to our buſineſs.</p>
            <p>For that which is paſt, there can be no queſtion made, whether that be a time for Work which remains yet to be done, for it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laps'd and gone, and being once loſt, is irrecoverable; we may more eaſily recall the River that ſlides inſenſibly by, haſting to the Ocean, than recover the dayes that are ſilently ſtollen on towards Eternity; there is no uſe to be made of the time paſt, but only this, by reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon what we have loſt or idly miſpent, to quicken and awaken our ſelves to the more careful improvement of what remains. 'Tis impertinent to wiſh that we had our time again, ſince that cannot be, all our wiſdom in this caſe is to lay the faſter hold upon what we yet have.</p>
            <p>This therefore being granted, that the time that is paſt is none of ours, and cannot now be imployed in Work, yet it may be hoped that what is to come may be counted our own, and that we have a better hold of that: 'Tis true, at preſent we are not diſpoſed for Work, or are otherwiſe imployed; but we are Young, or hope to live long, or hope at leaſt that we ſhall not dye yet; and ſo hope we may have time enough for Work hereafter.</p>
            <p>This is the uſual Plea that men make for delaying their Work till the time to come, and this is the ruiu of many a one, and a fatal Snare in which Satan entangles many an unwary Soul, while he beats them off from what is preſent and ſure, and turns them over to what is future and contingent. He perſwades them 'tis too ſoon to repent and reform yet, that 'tis too early to ſadden and damp the jollity and briskneſs of their Youth, with the ſad enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of ſorrow and repentance, or with the melancholly appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of Death and Judgment; another time he perſwades them to be more fit for thoſe things; and that Old Age, or at leaſt an Age more ſolid and ſtayed, more flegmatick and ſerious than the ſpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36418:13"/> of Youth, would be a ſeaſon much more proper to mind, and accompliſh that work. But while unwary man liſtens to theſe charms, the fatal hour ſteals on, and <hi>the night comes wherein no man can work:</hi> How many defer their Work till Old age, that dye in the prime of their Youth; and how many delay till too morrow, that never live to ſee that day? How many put off their Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance till they come to be ſick, whom death never gives ſo fair a warning to, but cuts them down unawares in the midſt of their health and ſtrength? Delays are dangerous, and if they are any where ſo, then much more here, where ſo great a concern as is our eternal welfare depends upon them. Wherefore againſt the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain and dangerous hopes of men that refuſe the preſent ſeaſon, and will ſtay for the time to come, before they apply themſelves to their Work, I ſhall endeavour to prove that the preſent time is the time in which we ought to do our Works; and for the proof of this I ſhall offer theſe three enſuing Conſiderations:</p>
            <p n="1">1. No man can be exempted from the ſervice of God for any time. For ſince it has been ſhewn already, that God made us for himſelf, it will neceſſarily follow, that there can be no time wherein it may be lawful for us to turn aſide from him, and to ſerve another; and if we muſt be alwayes employed in his ſervice, then ſurely we muſt now in this preſent be doing of his Work, which is a part of that time which he has given us to ſerve him in. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 31. And this the Apoſtle plainly proves, when he commands, <hi>Whatſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ever ye do, do all to the Glory of God;</hi> for if all our actions muſt tend to the Glory of God, then all our time muſt be lay'd out that way; becauſe our actions, and the time in which they are done cannot be ſevered; and if all our time muſt be ſpent for God, then without contradiction the preſent time muſt be ſo ſpent; this being (as was ſaid) a part of that time which is given us to ſerve him in: If then any one could either prove or imagine it lawful to be imploy'd at any time in the ſervice of Satan, or of our Luſts, then ſome reaſon might be ſhown why we ſhould not ſerve God now; but ſince it is horrible to imagine that any one can have leave from God to ſerve his En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>my, and ſince it plainly implies a contradiction that it can be lawful to be employed in ſo ſinful and unlawful a ſervice, it remains undeniably true, that God muſt be ſerved with the preſent time, and we muſt now be employed in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his work, becauſe all our time muſt be lay'd out in his ſervice, that is the preſent and the future time too; for he that is bound to ſerve God all the dayes of his life, is certainly bound to ſerve
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36418:13"/> ſerve God to day, this day being one of the days of his life; and if we muſt <hi>work the works of him that ſent us, while it is day,</hi> that is, while we live, if we live now, we muſt work now; and if at this preſent time it be day with us, then at this preſent time while it is ſo, we muſt be <hi>working the Works of him that ſent us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. But let it be farther conſidered, that this preſent time is the only time that is ours, or that we can be ſaid to be ſure of. What time is paſt is certainly and irrecoverably loſt, and that which is fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and to come is ours only by an incertain hope; and as it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that it may be Ours, ſo it under an equal poſſibility of never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, for it being only poſſible that we may live till too morrow, 'tis equally poſſible that we may die before. He therefore that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies God the preſent time, by that very denial ſins, and is unjuſt, becauſe he denies him what he is only ſure of, and puts him off with the promiſe of what is uncertain, and which he can never be ſure he ſhall be poſſeſſed of.</p>
            <p>And therefore if it be our duty to ſerve God at all, 'tis undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly our duty to ſerve him now, becauſe if we neglect the preſent time, in which we may do it, 'tis doubtful and incertain whether we ſhall ever live to ſee that day in which we promiſed to do it. What the Poet made an argument for preſent jollity and mirth, is much more ſtrong and concluding in this caſe, <hi>Sera nimis vita eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raſtina viv' hodie,</hi> he would have us <hi>be merry too day, for fear it ſhould be too late to begin it too morrow;</hi> but how much more reaſonably may it be urged, let us apply our ſelves to our buſineſs now, it may be too late to think on't hereafter.</p>
            <p>We have not the command of our own time, nor has God given any man among us the Leaſe of our Lives; we are all Tenants at Will, and muſt leave theſe Tenements of Clay whenſoever it pleaſes God to out us, ſince then God has hid from us the date of our Lives, we are mad as well as unjuſt to refuſe the preſent time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we do not know that we have any other.</p>
            <p>And this folly of neglecting to do our Work in the preſent time, might be further urged, as from the incertainty of our Lives, ſo alſo from the incertainty of aſſiſtance in our Work, or of acceptance of it when it is done.</p>
            <p>Too day the Spirit ſtrives, but we know not whither it will do ſo too morrow; only we know that God has ſaid, <hi>Gen. 6. 3. My Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſhall not always ſtrive with man.</hi> There is a time beyond which God will ſtrive no more, but will leave us to our ſelves; and if God
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36418:14"/> withdraw, though the day of Life may ſtill laſt, yet the day of Grace is done; and then though we may have a time to work, yet there is no heart to improve it; but our time is as <hi>Solomon</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains, <hi>Prov. 17. 16. A price in the hand of a fool to get wiſdom,</hi> that <hi>hath no heart to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But farther yet: From whence can we gather Confidence, or be aſſured that God will be content to wait our leiſure, and that he will accept of thoſe future ſervices that we reſolve to pay him? Sure 'tis not for need that he has of our ſervice, that he is forc'd to wait till we are at leiſure to ſerve him; for we benefit our ſelves and not him in doing our duty, and all our endeavours can add nothing to an Infinite Perfection. <hi>Eliphaz</hi> his Queſtion to <hi>Job</hi> proves this, <hi>Job 22. 3. Is it any pleaſure to the Almighty that thou art righteous, or is i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gain to him that thou makeſt thy ways perfect?</hi> and <hi>David</hi> plainly declares for the ſame thing, when in expreſs terms he ſays, <hi>Pſalm 16. 2. My Goodneſs extendeth not to thee.</hi> Upon what then do we preſume, while we waſte our preſent time in the drudgery of ſin, and then offer to God the dreggs and lees of our dayes; we ſpend our ſtrength and our prime that God delights in and requires, and when we are worn out in the ſervice of ſin, and can follow it no<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> longer, we then are willing to liſt our ſelves in the ſervice of God for a protection. How juſtly might God refuſe us then, when no Maſter elſe will entertain us; and ſince we refuſed his ſervice in the time he called for us, reject us from being his Servants when we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our ſelves to him?</p>
            <p n="3">3. But let us conſider once more and bluſh; let us ſee and be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of our unequal dealing herein. Whom do we prefer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and whoſe Yoak is it that we chuſe to take up in the firſt place? We will ſerve God hereafter, and take his Work in hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother time; let us ſee then to whom we dedicate the preſent time, and who is it whom now we ſerve.</p>
            <p>All our actions are by way of ſervice to one Maſter or another, as they have in them a tendency and ſubſerviency to ſome end. The World is divided between <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Belial,</hi> and all men are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers to God or the Devil.</p>
            <p>Behold then whom we ſerve; If we ſerve not God, we are employed in the Devils work and drudgery, we ſerve the luſts of the fleſh, are ſlaves to our own appetites, we run to Intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Wantonneſs, we ſerve an ambitious deſign, or a covetous mind, or things of this nature; and ſo under pretence of pleaſing our ſolves, do really ſerve, and are ſlaves to the Devil.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:36418:14"/>
            <p>And is this a ſervice to be choſen before that of the living God, that we muſt ſerve theſe now, and put off God till hereafter? Are theſe ſo deſirable Maſters, ſo good, ſo great Benefactors, that God muſt wait and ſtand by till they are ſerved in the firſt place? Is their ſervice ſo Honorable an Employment? Is it ſo rich and advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that this muſt have the preſent time? Is there ſo much pleaſure in being ſlaves to an unſatiable Appetite, or in being ridden by an untractable and exorbitant paſſion, that the Yoak of Chriſt which is eaſie, and his burden which is light, muſt be refuſed, to make way for this? Is the Devil ſo real a Friend, or our Luſts ſo really benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to us, that theſe muſt have the prime of our days and time? Let us conſider and bluſh, let us ſee and be aſhamed that we uſe our God ſo ingratefully here; 'tis God that is the Author of our time and being, and his Goodneſs and Bounty provides for us, and ſweetens our being to us, even the preſent time, that we lay out upon ſin, is his Gift (though given us for better ends) and that the time that is future comes up, and is preſent to us, is the effect of his patience and mercy towards us; and yet this time which he gives us for his own Service and Glory we rob him of, and lay it out in the drudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and bondage of his Enemies. This is an ingratitude that we ſhould be aſhamed of towards man, how much more ſhould we be aſhamed of it towards God, ſince here the ingratitude is infinitely greater.</p>
            <p>Shame then, if there be any in us, in theſe things, will prove that this preſent time ſhould be given to God; for if God hath it not, let us but conſider who hath, and this may be ſufficient to make us bluſh and tremble too.</p>
            <p>And this may ſuffice briefly to prove that the preſent time is the time in which we ought to <hi>work the Works of him that ſent us, we muſt work while it is day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. The Third Thing to be enquired into, Is the Reaſon why we muſt thus work theſe Works in the preſent time, and that as the Text gives it us, is, <hi>Becauſe the Night cometh when no man can work;</hi> the meaning of which is, when death once comes, it puts an end to all our working, and it will be too late to do then what ſhould have been done before.</p>
            <p>A Reaſon that wants nothing but our ſerious conſideration to make it invincible; and ſurely we are not therefore lazy and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, careleſs or remiſs in our duty, becauſe we want either Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or Motives that are proper and powerful to ſtir us up to the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36418:15"/> doing of it, but becauſe we want hearts to weigh the force of the Reaſon, and are either ſtupid or inconſiderate, when we have to do in matters of this nature.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore, To quicken and help your conſideration, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I conſider the reaſon it ſelf, by a ſtep or two lead you to the ſtrength and force of the Reaſon.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let this then be conſidered, That we have Work to do for God in the time that God has given us upon Earth; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are not at our own diſpoſal, and may not ſerve whom we pleaſe, or Work or let it alone as we find our ſelves inclined; but our Task is ſet, our Work is appointed, and woe be unto us if we do it not. For he that does not his Work, is idle and uſeleſs, and is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable Servant; and how dreadful a doom is paſt upon him, let us hear from the Lords own mouth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Mat. 25. 30. Caſt ye the unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſervant into utter darkneſs, there ſhall be weeping &amp; gnaſhing of teeth:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Let it be conſidered, That as we have Work to do, ſo we muſt come to an account for our Works, and we ſhall be examined both what we have done, and how. In plain terms there is a day of Judgment to come upon us all, and the work of that day will be to proceed upon, and according to our Works. This the Parable of the Talents proves, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. 19. this the Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> tells us, <hi>Heb. 9. 27. It is appointed unto men once to dye, but after this the Judgment.</hi> And this the <hi>Preacher</hi> concludes his Sermon with, as being Words of great weight, and as being deſirous to leave them well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixt in our memories, <hi>Eccleſ. 12. 14. God ſhall bring every Work into judgment, with every ſecret thing, whether it be good, or whether it be evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An account we muſt come to, and that ſo ſtrict, that none of our neglects or<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> loyterings can eſcape unobſerv'd; and a ſearch ſo punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and exact, that it will produce the very hidden things of darkneſs, and bring to light what we now hide ſo cloſe from the eyes of men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>What then might be ſome comfort to the ſlothful Servant here, the hopes that his Maſter may neglect or forget to call him to an account, can be no ſhelter nor ſupport in this caſe to him that neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects to do the Works that God ſent him into this World to do; for as his Work is ſet, ſo alſo a day of account is determined, and every Soul, and the ſecrets of it ſhall be brought into judgment.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Add to this, That when death comes, it will be too late to ſet about our. Work, that being a ſtate in which no Work can be done, and then we have the full force of the Reaſon apparent; we have Work to do, and we ſhall be called to an account whither we have
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36418:15"/> done it, and if death comes, it cannot be done, and therefore it follows, and the reaſon is too ſtrong to be deny'd, that we ought to do our Works while we have time and life, becauſe of approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing death, <hi>The night cometh when no man can work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now having thus conſidered the ſtrength of the Reaſon, wherein it lies; let me conſider the Reaſon it ſelf in its parts, and urge the neceſſity of our Working now, from ſuch conſiderations as the Reaſon it ſelf will allow: And here I ſhall betake my ſelf to the words of the Text, and conſider the Reaſon as it lies there; and ſo it may be taken into two parts, and yet either of them retain the force of a Reaſon to urge us to the duty under conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The night cometh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>When it is come, no work can be done in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. <hi>The night,</hi> that is death cometh; in which theſe things are imploy'd, which may ſerve to heighten our diligence, and to haſten us in our Work.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The night cometh,</hi> then death is certain, and will undoubtedly be with us, for in that it's ſaid it comes, it undeniably proves that there is ſuch a thing as death, ſince that which is not cannot come. And this is a thing not more certain in it ſelf, than it is evident and apparent to us, That we are Mortal, and when our part is acted, muſt go off the Stage of this World, conſtant and daily Experience teaches us, and proves it to us. This is the Path that is daily trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by all ſorts, ages, and conditions of men, the Young and Old, the Poor and Rich, Bond and Free, Male and Female, all meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the Chambers of Death, and lye down to reſt in the duſt. This is the common fate of Man kind, and that irreverſible Decree paſt at the firſt Tranſgreſſion, from which no man ordinarily is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt. <hi>Methuſelah</hi> ran a long Courſe, yet after Nine hundred ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and nine years he dyed; and <hi>Abraham</hi> lived well, and was the Father of the Faithful, and the Friend of God, yet after an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred threeſcore and fifteen Years he gave up the Ghoſt, and dyed.</p>
            <p>And there want not dayly <hi>Memento</hi>'s of our Mortality, even in all thoſe things that are daily obvious to our eyes; the conſtant courſe of Winter and Summer, and of Day and Night put us in mind of our putting off the Glories of this Life, and of our ſleeping in death. The Winter ſtrips the Earth of her glory and beauty, and leaves her naked, it hinders and determines her fruitful ſeaſons, and death takes down our Pride and Pomp, and tyes our hands that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not work.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:36418:16"/>
            <p>At night we uncloath and go to bed, and how far ſoever we ramble in the day, we then leave our Labours, and confine our ſelves to a narrower compaſs to take our reſt till morning: And in death we ſtrip and lye down in the Grave, and our Bodies take their long ſleep till dooms day morning wake us again. Our great Eſtates, and numerous Lands ſhrink up in death to ſix foot of Earth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and our ſtately Seats, and ceiled Rooms, and coſtly Furnitures, give way to a Winding-ſheet, a Tomb, and a Coffin. Thus Night and Winter are fit Emblems to us of Death, and ſerious <hi>Memonto</hi>'s of our mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſtate.</p>
            <p>The certainty then of this ſhould mind us of the work we have to do, and engage us to be diligent at it; our time is ſtated, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more ſure than that its end will come, and death will over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take us; our Work is appointed, and ſo is our time too; why then do we waſte or trifle away that time which hath its limits fixed, and will certainly be determined by death? Why then do we project great things for our ſelves here, which death will ſtrip us of, and turn aſide from that work that God has appointed us to do; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of which no death can deprive us of? This very Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that death is certain, ſhould make us more careful in our work, and ſit more looſe, and be more indifferent to any advantages or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments of this life. If our work be done, death cannot rob us of the reward of that, but may be embraced as an advantage, being a <hi>Reſt from our Labours,</hi> and a refuge from every Calamity that here we are burdened with, <hi>Rev. 14. 13. Bleſſed are the dead which dye in the Lord, from henceforth, yea ſaith the Spirit, that they may reſt from their Labours, and their Works do follow them.</hi> But for all other things which are the advantages of this Life, only death robs us of them all, and brings the Great and Mighty into an equal ſtate with the Poor, Ignoble, and Mean. The Grave knows no difference, and the Worm knows no diſtinction betwixt finer and courſer fleſh. He that marches to the Grave in a ſtately array, and with a ſolemn pomp, and he that ſteals ſilently into the Chambers of death, and makes no noiſe nor buſtle at his going, both find an equal Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the duſt, and both have the ſame Kindred and Relations there, and both with <hi>Job</hi> muſt ſay <hi>chap. 17. 14. To Corruption thou art my Father, to the Worm thou art my Mother and my Siſter:</hi> Our Greatneſs leaves us at the Grave, and no diſtinctions remain after death, but ſuch as a faithful ſerving of God, and a conſcientious induſtry in our Works may give us. Why then do we neglect our
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36418:16"/> work that would live with us beyond death, and are fond of things that periſh as to us by it? ſince <hi>the night cometh,</hi> that is Death is certain.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The night cometh,</hi> Then Death is at hand, it cometh! Then it is haſtning on towards us, it's already in the way, and onwards in its journey to us.</p>
            <p>And this the ſhortneſs of our Lives, (when they are at their lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt) plainly ſpeaks. If once we are born, even by the courſe of Nature, we have not long to live, and threeſcore years and ten, which is the age of a man, is but a poor pittance of time, if it be compared to the Eternity that depends upon it. The very firſt ſtep that we ſet into this World, is onwards towards Death, and to the Youngeſt as well as to the Old, it may be ſaid death cometh. Our Life is compared to a Race, as ſwift, as ſhort as that, the ſtarting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place is from the Womb, and the Goal is the Grave, and all the while between our Birth and Deceaſe, we are in our Race haſting on to death. As ſoon as our day begins to dawn, the night alſo begins to haſten its approaches; and we do no ſooner begin to live, but we are going onwards towards death.</p>
            <p>How ſhould this Conſideration then haſten us in our Work, and make us more diligent and induſtrious, our time is ſhort, and the end of it at hand, our Work is great, and we have much to do; how unreaſonable is it then for us to loyter or be idle, and how much more for us to be doing of Evil, which muſt be unravelled and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done again? All our time is little enough for our buſineſs, there can be none to ſpare for evil ends, or for a forreign ſervice; our End draws on whither we mind it or no: Prudence then would teach us to ply our Work, that the end of our time and our work may meet together. Let us always then be well employed, that death may find us ſo when it comes, and that time cannot be far off; <hi>The night cometh,</hi> that is, death is at hand.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The Night cometh:</hi> And this implies that the time of death is uncertain; <hi>the night cometh!</hi> Then no man knows how near death may be, all that is ſaid of it, is, that it cometh; this makes the thing certain: but there is no determination when it comes, and this leaves the time of it uncertain as to us. 'Tis true, it may be coming, and yet may be a great way off, and it is as true, it may be at hand, and juſt now at the door.</p>
            <p>And this is a thing ſo daily made good to us by Experience, that it juſtly becomes matter of great wonder, that men regard and lay
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36418:17"/> it to heart no more; we ſee daily men likely to live long, on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den cut down, and their days are come to an end; when we thought they had been ſcarcely arrived at the middle of them. And we have now another freſh inſtance of it ſet before us; and here is one gone to his long-home, who according to the courſe of Nature had lived but half the Age of a man.</p>
            <p>And this ſtill adds more force to the Reaſon, To be mindful of our buſineſs, and to haſten our Work, for we know not how ſo on we may dye. Inſtances of ſudden and unexpected Mortality are not rare, which makes it the more to be admired, that thoſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main will flatter themſelves with the hopes of a longer time here, when they ſee ſo great experiences to the contrary. How mad are we then that put off the doing of that Work which is ſo neceſſary to be done, to that time which it is abſolutely uncertain whether we ſhall ever have or no. That our Work be done is neceſſary, that if we neglect the preſent time, we ſhall have another to do it in is uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; ſo that we venture our Souls upon a Contingency, and hang our Eternal Happineſs upon that which may very poſſibly fail us. A piece of Imprudence that were ridiculous in our Worldly affairs, and yet men are not aſhamed thus to act in a caſe that concerns Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. The Plow-man will take his Seaſon, and the Marriner his Wind and Tide; the Trades man will not let ſlip his Market; and every man thinks it wiſdom to take a good Offer while we may have it, for fear we ſhould miſs of the like again; and yet in things of far greater Concern than theſe, we are not aware that we egregiouſly play the fool's in turning off our buſineſs till hereafter, and in letting ſlip the fair proffers and opporrunities of the preſent ſeaſon. So ſad and miſerable a thing it is to be blind in Spiritual things, and to be habituated to Evil. An ordinary prudence would teach us to act more like men, and to be more diligent in our Work in the time we have, ſince we are not ſure of any more, <hi>for the night cometh,</hi> and death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is ſure, but the time is uncertain, and no man knows how ſoon it may come.</p>
            <p>And thus the conſideration of Death is and ought to be a Motive to us to improve our time, and work while we may, <hi>for we muſt dye,</hi> and that ere-long; and who knows how ſoon? but then we have to enquire into the reaſon or ſtrength of this Motive, which makes the conſideration of death to come an Argument for our preſent dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence; and that lies in theſe words, <hi>When no man can Work.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:36418:17"/>
            <p>2. This is then the Second and ſtrongeſt part of the Reaſon, <hi>When the night is come, no Work can be done in it:</hi> We had need be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in our Work while we have time, for if death comes it will be too late to do it, or to ſet about it; we muſt work now in this life, or not at all. <hi>Pſalm 6. 5. In death</hi> (ſays the <hi>Pſalmiſt) there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of thee.</hi> All our VVorks there ceaſe, death puts an end to every contrivance and deſign, and whatſoever remains to do, when we come to die, remains undone to all Eternity; for the ſtate of death is an unalterable ſtate, <hi>As the Tree falls ſo it lies, and as death leaves us, ſo judgment finds us;</hi> what we are then, ſuch we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue for ever; for the night being once come, <hi>no man can work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now our working may be conſidered as it is employed; either,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In doing what was never done before; or,</p>
            <p n="2">2. In mending what was ill done, and in both Caſes, <hi>the night comes, when no man can work;</hi> our ſtate is fixt by death, and our works are at an end both wayes, and then we can neither begin any work, nor polliſh, nor finiſh what was before begun.</p>
            <p n="1">1. VVe work in doing what was never before done, but no man can work thus in death. If we have not begun to ſerve God in this life, it will be too late to ſet to that VVork when we are dead, for that ſtate and time is all appointed for reward, and nothing at all for Work; it will be too late then to begin to love or ſerve God, for then it will be only enquired what we have already done, and not what we would now do. This is the time that is given us in order to Eternity, and upon the improvement of this, the determination of that Eternity whether it be to happineſs or miſery do's depend.</p>
            <p>After death ſucceeds the Judgment, and <hi>every man ſhall be judged according to his Works;</hi> Our<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> VVorks then are done when we die, and after death nothing more remains, but to receive our judgment according to them. This is the time of our VVork, that the time of our VVages; here is our Seed time, there is our Harveſt, <hi>Gal. 6. 7, 8. And whatſoever a man ſoweth, that ſhall he alſo reap; for he that ſoweth to his fleſh, ſhall of the fleſh reap corruption; but he that ſoweth to the Spirit, ſhall of the Spirit reap life everlaſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This then ſtrongly enforces upon us the duty of <hi>working while it is day,</hi> for if we dye and leave our VVork undone, there is no finiſhing of it in the Grave. Let us weigh them, and conſider how ſad their ſtate, how miſerable their condition muſt needs be who are preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by death, and die and their work is undone. VVho can lie down in Everlaſting burnings? and who can ſtand before an incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:36418:18"/> God? <hi>for our God is a conſuming fire.</hi> How ſad would it be to ſee a Soul rouling in endleſs flames, and too late curſing its own negligence and folly? how ſad would it be to hear him wiſhing in vain for the time that was idled away and miſpent, and to ſee the anguiſh of his Soul, becauſe his work is undone, and now remains no time to do it? And let us ſuppoſe this to be our caſe; for if we are not wiſe betimes, it will certainly be ſo: Let us ſuppoſe our Souls in ſuch a ſtate as this is, that we may awaken our ſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and while we have yet a day upon Earth, may be wiſe to employ and lay it out for God. For happy are they that ſee their folly betimes, and are betimes convinc'd that that their work is yet to do, while the time yet laſts in which it may be done. Sad and unſpeakably miſerable are thoſe convictions which are firſt found in Hell, for ſince they cannot there put us upon work, their effects can be nothing but Eternal deſperation.</p>
            <p>Let us then be wiſe in time; let us remember that there is no work in death, and withall remember that <hi>the night cometh;</hi> and let this excite us to diligence in our duty, and haſten us <hi>to work the works of him that ſent us, while it is day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. VVork may be emplyed, in mending what is done ill or amiſs. And in this ſenſe too there is <hi>no man can work when the night comes.</hi> It will be too late then to review our works with hopes to repair their defects. Alas, the time for theſe things is at an end, and 'tis now too late as well to mend as to make.</p>
            <p>Repentance and Amendment are the works of this life, ſingle repentance is part of the miſery of the next. Hell is full of Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, for there is none that comes into that place, but does ſoon repent him of his former negligence, and that he improved his time no better, that he minded no more the grand Concern, and made no better proviſion for his eternal ſtate; but this ſorrow cannot end in joy, nor this repentance be to ſalvation; for 'tis a repentance without a reformation, and a ſorrow for ſin when 'tis too late to forſake it. As Death is inexorable, and will not be deferred by entreaties, ſo is the judgment too, and will not be altered by fruitleſs tears and vain promiſes of amendment. Let St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> read us our doom in this caſe, <hi>Venturum eſt judicium, crit &amp; tunc poenitentia ſed infructuoſa.</hi> The judgment is coming, and then men will repent, but it will be fruitleſs. It will be ſo in reſpect of the product of fruits meet for repentance, the forſaking of ſin, and leading a new life; and therefore it will be fruitleſs too as to the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:36418:18"/> ends of repentance, or as to the promiſes that attend upon our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance here, the blotting out of our ſins and a remembring our tranſgreſſions no more. VVhat we do muſt be done here, there is no returning from the dead to reform; nor is there room for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and reformation in the grave. Let the Papiſt talk of their Purgatory as a middle ſtate after death, where ſouls make ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for their neglects in this life, and being purified by fire, paſs from thence to heaven. The Scripture tells us of no middle ſtate after death between heaven and hell, and of no ſatisfaction but what Chriſt made by his obedience and ſufferings When we die, we are determined to one of the two, and all ſouls paſs, either to eternal bliſs, from whence is no fear of falling; or to everlaſting wo, from whence is no hopes of returning. And what ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſoever can be made to divine juſtice for ſin, it muſt either be obtained by ſaith in Chriſt, and that's onely attainable here; or elſe 'tis made by our ſufferings after death, and there no ſufferings of ours can ſuffice, that are not eternal.</p>
            <p>So that what-ever can conduce to our eternal welfare, is onely to be done and obtained here; while we live there is hope, if death once ſeize us, our ſtate is determined, our work is at an end<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it's neceſſary then that we work the works of him that ſent us <hi>while it is day;</hi> and that becauſe the night cometh, <hi>when no man can work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the uſe of all then be, to perſwade us to remember and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice our duty now in time, to improve the preſent ſeaſon, and to uſe the day while it laſts; and ſince we have heard that there is in death no doing the work that we left undone, nor any mending that which was done ill; let all ſerve to ſtir us up to diligence both at and in our work.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To diligence at our work; That is, Conſtantly to employ our ſelves in the works of him that ſent us; to let paſs no opportunity of ſerving God either in the duties of his worſhip or in doing good in our generations. Our work is great, our time is ſhort, we had need make haſte and ply it hard. Death is coming, and the peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od of our dayes is at hand, where it will be too late to ſet about our buſineſs; let us then now work the works of him that ſent us; <hi>and happy is he, whom when his Lord comes he ſhall find ſo doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Let it ſtir us up to diligence in our work, To do well what we do; for there is no amendment in the grave. Let us not think that any thing will ſerve the turn, or that God will be put off with our
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:36418:19"/> work ſlightly done. As we muſt do the works that God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, ſo muſt they be done as he requires, or elſe we may pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh for failing in the manner of our duties, as well as for negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting them as to their matter. Death will be ſad to the unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and the lewd and proſane may well dread that day; but it will be as ſad with the hypocrite as with them, for the hypocrite and unbeliever ſhall have their portion together. For he that has done his work onely to be ſeen of men, or barely to ſtop the mouth of conſcience; he that works onely for by ends, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploys himſelf, though in the works that are required, yet for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ends than God appointed, ſerves himſelf and not God; and becomes a ſlave to himſelf and his own intereſt, and has not done the works of him that ſent him; becauſe he did his works for other ends than God allows. The judgment is at hand, and as we ſhall be judged according to our works, ſo ſhall our works be call'd into judgment too, and be ſeverely ſcann'd what they are; and happy is he and onely he whoſe work will abide the trial.</p>
            <p>And now to ſhut up all in the words of the Preacher, <hi>Eccleſ. 12. 13, 14. Let us hear the concluſion of the whole matter; Fear God and keep his Commandments, for this is the whole duty of man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For God ſhall bring every work into judgment, with every ſecret thing; whether it be good or whether it be evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="section">
               <p>And thus I have done with my Text, but the occaſion upon which it was choſen adminiſters farther<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> matter of diſcourſe ſtill. As I have ſpoken thus much to you from theſe words, ſo I ſuppoſe 'tis expected I ſhould ſpeak ſomething more concerning the perſon whoſe Deceaſe gave occaſion to this Sermon.</p>
               <p>You are not ignorant that my uſuall Cuſtom heretofore in this Caſe has been either to be ſilent altogether, or to ſay but little. For I confeſs my ſelf too little a friend to that common uſage, to give a fair <hi>Encomium</hi> of a perſon whom I knew not very well, meerly becauſe it has been a cuſtom to praiſe Folks when they are dead; and to conclude a Funeral Sermon with a Commendation. But I know you expect that I ſhould break both my Cuſtom and my Silence here; and this I am the rather inclin'd to do, becauſe my acquaintance with him while he liv'd, makes me able to ſpeak truth and yet to ſpeak well of him now he is dead.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:36418:19"/>
               <p>And therefore I ſhould think my ſelf unjuſt both to him and you, ſhould I be ſilent here. Unjuſt to him, if I ſhould deny to give him that Elogy which is his due; and unjuſt to you, in denying to ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ſo good a Pattern and example for your Imitation.</p>
               <p>It is I confeſs an agravation to our ſorrow, and like grating up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Sore, to remember what a one we have loſt; yet ſince he is loſt to us, there is this comfort in it, that he was ſuch a one. 'Tis our ſorrow that ſo good a man is dead, for the greater is our loſſe; yet, tis an alleviation of our ſorrow that he was ſo good that died; ſince 'tis his unſpeakable advantage.</p>
               <p>His death indeed was ſudden and immature, if we reſpect the time of his life, having run but a little more then half the length of his Race; but yet I have reaſon to believe that it was neither ſudden nor immature as to his readineſs and preparations for it. For ſince death is never ſudden indeed, and ſo unwelcome, but to thoſe that have not done the works of him that ſent them (they may well wiſh the night farther off that have all their work to do) I have reaſon to ſay that upon this account his death to him, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it may be to us, was neither ſudden nor immature.</p>
               <p>For to conſider the works we have to do, either relating immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to God, or as they concern our Neighbour, we ſhall find him to have been a labourer in both, and that no ſluggiſh one<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and a Work-man that we hope is not now aſham'd.</p>
               <p>He was one that made a Conſcience of honouring God in the duties of his worſhip and ſervice, and one whoſe attendance upon the ordinances we have reaſon to believe, was for better ends then to make a ſhew, and to be ſeen of men. His attendance upon the publick worſhip was frequent and conſtant, as could be expected from one ſo remote; his hearing was with attention and diligence, and his converſation ſhew'd that all was not loſt that he heard, but that the Seed ſown was received into a good and honeſt heart. He was a conſtant gueſt at the Table of the Lord, rarely if ever miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of any opportunity to partake of that ordinance, a thing the more remarkable in our times, in which that ordinance is fallen un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a great neglect, and in moſt places this Table is but very thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet with gueſts. His behaviour there was with that reverence that became a creature in ſo near approaches to his God; and his deportment was ſuch, as was to me a ſign of his previous prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               <p>But all this was publick, and what was obvious to the eye of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:36418:20"/> the world, where the Hypocrite may ſtrain hard to make as fair a ſhew. And as to him, I durſt not build my hopes upon this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, if this were all the foundation I had for them.</p>
               <p>Let us follow him then from the place of Gods publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip into his Family, and obſerve his deportment there; and there we might ſee that he left not his Religion at Church, as having no uſe for it any where elſe; but he made it his Companion at home as well as here, and made it his buſineſs to ſerve God in his houſe as well as at the Church.</p>
               <p>Beſides his joyning in prayer with his Family, he had his ſtated times for private prayer, which he conſtantly attended to by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and often took in his Wife to be a partner with him in them. And his courſe and way of life, and his diſcourſe, as occaſion was offered, ſhewed that theſe exerciſes of Religion were not counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit or forced, or were meerly a mask put on for a ſhew, but that they proceeded from a principle of piety within, and from a heart ſeaſoned with grace, and a real deſire after that which is good.</p>
               <p>At the firſt entrance of that Diſeaſe into his Family, of which he died, I can bear him wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <note place="margin">The Small Pox.</note> that he took it as became a Chriſtian to do; neither ſlighting the providence nor ſlaviſhly afraid of it; neither deſpiſing the chaſtnings of the Almighty, nor fainting under his corrections; but cheerfully caſting himſelf into the arms of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, contentedly reſolv'd to abide by what God ſhould deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine concerning him.</p>
               <p>As to the time of his laſt Sickneſs which was but ſhort, his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe was ſuch as ſometimes took away the uſe of his underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; yet then, when his tongue, that unruly member, was at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to walk at its own pleaſure without the guidance of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, it was never heard to utter any thing that was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of, or unbecoming a ſober or a Chriſtian man: An evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent argument that it was ſo accuſtomed to the words of Sober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Truth, that it knew not how to go out of thoſe paths, when left to range at its own liberty.</p>
               <p>He was not without ſerious apprehenſions of his approaching end; and then when the hypocrites hopes fail him and all falſe grounds of hopes or peace vaniſh, his comfort then ſtood firm; and though the Tempter was not wanting in his aſſaults, yet he could not deſtroy his peace. He call'd to thoſe that were buſie
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:36418:20"/> about him in helping him againſt his bodily diſtemper, <hi>Come let us ſoberly think what Chriſt hath done for poor ſinners;</hi> and being told that the ground of hope was in the infinite mercies of God thorow Jeſus Chriſt, he reply'd, <hi>There in is my comfort.</hi> And an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other time he told them, <hi>The Devil hath ſet upon me and hath ſtruck me to the heart, but I have overcome him and he is gone from me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if we conſider the other part of his work, in that relation that he ſtood in towards man, the moſt part of you know as well as I, that it was ſuch as no man could blame. And without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending to particulars, it might be enough for his commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but to obſerve that univerſal regret that is among all men of all ſorts, that had but any acquaintance with him, for the loſs of him. For if we conſider him in thoſe particular relations in which God had ſet him, as a Son, as a Husband, as a Father; in thoſe three he might well ſtand to very many as a pattern of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, of kindneſs, and of care.</p>
               <p>He was a dutiful Son, and poſſibly without injury to any, it might be added as ever any man had; and that not onely in his childhood and youth, but when he was grown up, and became a Father himſelf. He never diminiſhed his due reſpects to his aged Father when he became a man and was at his own diſpoſal; and by his tenderneſs and care of his health, ſhewed that he was far from their ſordid and unnatural mind, who think that life (though it be the life of a father) too long, that ſtands between them and an Eſtate. He was the Staffe of his aged Fathers dayes, and the delight of his eyes, and was never known to be a grief to him till now.</p>
               <p>He was a kind and loving Husband to his Wife, and as God had bleſſed them with a numerous Iſſue between them, ſo he had bleſt them alſo with a mutual love and complacency one in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; and that to ſuch a degree, that what that Roman ſaid in his Funeral Elegy of his <note place="margin">Se nunquam redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe in gratiam cum Matre.</note> Mother, <hi>That for thirty years ſpace he was never reconciled to her.</hi> Meaning that there was never any difference between them that needed a reconciliation; may be ſaid truly of them: <hi>That for the ſpace of fifteen years,</hi> which was all the time they lived together, <hi>they were never reconciled;</hi> for that ſuppoſes a difference to have benn: but in all that time there happened none betvveen them.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:36418:21"/> For it comes from the mouth of his own dear Conſort (whom he hath left ſo much the more diſconſolate, by the remembrance of ſo great kindneſs) that in all the time they lived together, there was never any contradiction between them in anger.</p>
               <p>As a Father, he was tender over his children, careful of their Education, and provident to lay up for them.</p>
               <p>And now if we take a view of him in a large capacity, and as ſtanding in a wider relation, we ſhall find the ſame perfume of a good name, following him ſtill: I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ve conſider him in general as a man, and at large, as a Citizen of the World, we ſhall find that he did well become that ſtation, and well diſcharge the duties of that relation.</p>
               <p>God had given him a plentiful eſtate, and he had withal a heart to enjoy and uſe it, a bleſſing that does not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wayes attend upon the poſſeſſion of riches; he lived comfort <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> upon what he had, and was never a ſlave to his own poſſeſſions.</p>
               <p>And as he did not rob himſelf (for I count every Miſer a thief to his own body) ſo neither did he rob the poor, neither in grind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them with oppreſſion, nor in with-holding their hire, nor in being ſpare in his Contributions towards their relief as he ſaw need; nor was he injurious to any other in any of his dealings with them, no man being able to charge him in any inſtance with the leaſt tinctures of oppreſſion, wrong, or fraud.</p>
               <p>If we take him as to his carriage among men, we might ſee him of a meek and quiet ſpirit, neither making contention nor delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in it.</p>
               <p>He was aſſable and courteous to his inſeriours, and though he had fair advantages above many others in this world, yet was not he proud, nor his heart lift up to deſpiſe thoſe that were meaner and below himſelf.</p>
               <p>He was a friend that was faithful and truſty, and one that was willing to do good, and to be helpful to others. His friend need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to extort a kindneſs from him by importunities, or repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed requeſts, but he was ready (where it lay in his power) to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent his asking, by doing him good.</p>
               <p>As to his Morals, they were ſuch as deſerve a peculiar remarque in theſe licentious times; wherein <hi>Diogenes,</hi> were he alive, might take his Candle and Lanthorn again at noon day to go ſeek for a ſober temperate young Gentleman. He was one amongſt thoſe few that wanted nothing to make him run with the herd and to be
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:36418:21"/> debaucht, as the moſt are, but an inclination to it. For he wanted neither youth nor wealth; his years were not ſuch as made him paſt thoſe extravagances, and he had a purſe better able to bear it than many of them have; and aſſociates to allure to and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in ſuch courſes could not long be wanting in ſo degenerous an age as ours. But yet for all theſe inducements, he kept him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf pure from the pollutions of the age wherein he lived; being managed by a ſpirit free from that ſordidneſs that rules too much now in the moſt; that can reliſh no pleaſures but what are ſenſual, and too plainly bruitiſh. I have heard him often take occaſion to diſcourſe concerning the pleaſures and advantages of a holy life, of the comfort and ſerenity of a good conſcience, againſt the clamors and troubles and ſcoffings of this World: And to one that told him how much piety and vertue, and the ſerious practice of religion was diſcredited in the world, and accounted ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and fooliſh, his anſwer was, <hi>Let them ſtay till the end, and ſee who is the fool then.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to that end he is now arrived, where I queſtion not but he enjoys the benefit and reward of his works; and knows by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that (what-ever the mad world eſteems it to be) 'tis nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ridiculous nor fooliſh to be ſober or pious; and that 'tis not onely our duty, but alſo highly worth the while, <hi>to work the works of him that ſent us while it is day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus far I have been able to ſpeak of him from my own obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, and to give this account of him from my own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; having been beholding to the relations of others but for three inſtances in all that I have ſaid. Had I call'd in help, or made it my buſineſs to make Collections, or ſtudied to ſet him out to the full, I might have given a larger Character, and a much fairer <hi>Encomium</hi> of him; and yet perhaps not have ſaid more than the ſubject would well bear. But let this ſuffice.</p>
               <p>But now, of what uſe is all this that hath been ſpoken of him, or to what purpoſe? Is it for his ſake that is dead and departed from us? Alas he needs it not, 'tis no advantage to him now, that we think or ſpeak well of him: 'Tis no addition to his glory above, that his aſhes are perfumed with the odour of a good name; or that his memory is valuable or precious amongſt us.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:36418:22"/>
               <p>The deſign of all this that I have ſaid of him is your benefit, and he being dead, yet ſpeaketh to you, and reads you a uſeful Leſſon.</p>
               <p>In that he ſo lived and ſo died, lived ſo well and died ſo ſoon; there is matter of direction for your practice in both of them: in the one he is a pattern, and in the other a monitor; and ſo both by his life and by his death he ſpeaketh to you.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By his Life. Here is offered to you a fair pattern for your imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; for therefore are the dead commended, and a recital made of their vertues, that the living may be provoked thereby and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to do well. A good name is a bleſſing that is promiſed to good actions; and the Wiſe-man tells us, <hi>Prov 10. 7. That memory of the juſt is bleſſed, when the name of the wicked ſhall rot.</hi> But this, as I ſaid, cannot reach to the ſtate of glorified ſouls; the greateſt uſe of their good name, is for thoſe that ſurvive: that others may be encouraged to do as they have done. This the Apoſtle calls upon the <hi>Philipians</hi> to do, and this is our duty alſo as well as theirs. <hi>Phil. 4. 8. Whatſoever things are true, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver things are honeſt, whatſoever things are juſt, whatſoever things are pure, whatſoever things are lovely, whatſoever things are of good report; if there be any vertue, if there be any praiſe, to think on theſe things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. By his Death. And ſo while we ſee a young man taken off almoſt in the midſt of his dayes, it gives a fair warning to you that ſurvive, to husband and improve your time. This ſhews that it's dangerous to delay and put off our work till another time, or to truſt to Youth, or to hope for too morrow; for Youth cannot ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us from death, and too morrow often failes thoſe that ſtay and hope for it. We ſee here that Death hath inverted the order of Nature, and the Father cloſing the Eyes of his Son, whom he hoped might have out-liv'd him long. The leſſon then that his death reads us, is this, That life is uncertain; and this ſhould make us afraid to defer our work, leſt the night ſhould ſteal upon us ere we are aware of it or prepared for it. Let every one of us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reſolve upon our work, and ſet roundly to it; let us take the preſent time, which God allows us to work in, and requires to be ſpent in his ſervice; none ever complain'd in the end of beginning this work too ſoon; when many have periſhed and been loſt for
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:36418:22"/> ever; who alwayes thought it too ſoon yet to begin. Death draws on, whether we will provide for it or no; and whether we work or loyter, the fatal hour ſtill approaches; it cannot be far off to them from whom it is fartheſt; and by this inſtance it appears it may be nearer than we are aware of. Having then before us an example that proves the truth both of the Text and Sermon, <hi>Let us work the works of him that ſent us, while it is day; the night cometh, when no man can work.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag. 29. line 15. read</hi> imply'd; <hi>p. 30. l. 28. r.</hi> Life only,</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_notice">
            <head>
               <hi>Books ſold by</hi> Tho. Parkhurſt <hi>at the Bible and Three Crowns in</hi> Cheapſide.</head>
            <p>A Morning Exerciſe againſt Popery.</p>
            <p>The Young Man's Inſtructer, and Old Mans Remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer. A large Expoſition on the Aſſemblies Catechiſm. By <hi>T. Doolittel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Forty ſix Sormons on the whole Eighth Chapter of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A Practical Expoſition on the Four ſelect Pſalms. <hi>viz.</hi> 4th, 42, 51, 63. The whole being in 45 Sermons. Both by <hi>Tho. Horton,</hi> D. D, late Preacher at St. <hi>Hellens, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Childs Delight,</hi> with Pictures for teaching <hi>Engliſh,</hi> to which is added an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Grammar.</p>
            <p>Reading and Spelling made eaſie, wherein all the words of our
<pb facs="tcp:36418:23"/> 
               <hi>Engliſh Bible,</hi> are ſet down in an Alphabetical Order, and divided into their diſtinct Syllables. By <hi>Tho Lye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Liberty for Captives. By <hi>Tho. Doolitel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Plain Mans Defence againſt Popery, wherein Popery is proved to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> againſt Scripture; fitted for the meaneſt capacity. By a Chaplain to a Perſon of Honour.</p>
            <p>Two Diſputations of Original Sin. By <hi>Rich. Baxter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Expoſition on the whole Epiſtle to the <hi>Coloſſians.</hi> By <hi>John Dallie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Treatiſe of Holy Violence for Heaven.</p>
            <p>A Plea for the Godly.</p>
            <p>The Duty of Self-denyal. All three by <hi>Tho. Watſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Immortality of the Soul. By <hi>Tho. Wadſworth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Almoſt Chriſtian. By <hi>Matth. Mead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Spiritual Wiſdom improved againſt Temptation. By <hi>Matt. Mead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Method of Meditation. By <hi>Tho. White.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Godly Mans Ark. By <hi>Edm. Calamy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Heart-Treaſury, firſt and ſecond parts.</p>
            <p>Cloſet-Prayer. Both by <hi>Oliver Heywood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Treatiſe of Quenching the Spirit. By <hi>Theoph. Pawlwheel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sinfulneſs of Sin. By <hi>Ralph Venning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Myſterial Union between Chriſt and Believers. And, Sober Singularity. By <hi>Rowland Stedman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Janeway</hi>'s Life.</p>
            <p>Saints Encouragement. Both by <hi>James Janeway.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Spirit of Prayer. By <hi>Nath. Vincent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Plain Expoſition of the Aſſemblies Catechiſm, By <hi>Tho. Lye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Weaving Spiritualized; or, The Weaver's Pocket Book<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> By <hi>J. C.</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>Eighteen Sermons by <hi>William Whittaker,</hi> with his Funeral Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. By Dr. <hi>Anſley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reformation or Ruin. By <hi>Tho. Hotchkis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Life of Dr. <hi>Staunton,</hi> with a Dialogue between a Miniſter and a Stranger; and a Diſcourſe of Chriſtian Conference.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Index Biblicus,</hi> or, A Table of the Holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>A Plain and Familiar Diſcourſe concerning the Lords Supper By <hi>Rich. Kidder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antapologia,</hi> or, A Diſcourſe of Excuſes; ſetting forth the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety and vanity of them. By <hi>Jo. Sheffield.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:36418:23"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36418:24"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36418:24"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
